Guide to the Chinese Nationality Room Committee Collection, 1929-1939 UA.40.04
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Chinese Nationality Room Committee Collection
1929-1939
ULS Archives & Special Collections
University of Pittsburgh. Nationality Rooms Program. Chinese Nationality Room Committee.
UA.40.04
2.5 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
The Chinese Nationality Room Committee Collection holds records pertaining to the design, funding, and construction of the Chinese Nationality Room in the Cathedral of Learning. The committee was established in 1929, and the room was dedicated on October 6, 1939. The collection is composed of correspondence, design notes, blueprints, newspaper clippings, financial reports, meeting minutes, summaries of daily progress, photographs, pamphlets, invitations, and publicity pertaining to the establishment of the Chinese Nationality Room.
Scope and Content Notes
The Chinese Nationality Room Committee Collection is composed of documents related to the design, funding, and construction of the Chinese Nationality Room in the Cathedral of Learning. The bulk of these records date from between the start of planning in 1929 and the dedication of the room in 1939. These documents consist of correspondence, primarily between Ruth Crawford Mitchell, members of the Chinese Nationality Room Committee, and the architects Teng Kwei and Henry K. Murphy; design notes; blueprints; newspaper clippings; financial reports; committee meeting minutes; summaries of daily progress; photographs; pamphlets; invitations; and publicity pertaining to the Chinese Nationality Room and the Chinese and Chinese-American community in Pittsburgh. Materials are primarily in English, though some are in Traditional Chinese characters.
History
The Chinese Nationality Room Committee, or the Committee on China Memorial Room, was established in 1929 by the Chinese Students Club to raise funds for and coordinate the construction of the Chinese Classroom in the Cathedral of Learning. After fundraising among Chinese communities in Pittsburgh and on the East Coast, the Chinese Nationalist government agreed to donate $10,000 to the project after a petition from the committee chairman, Dr. Chi Fang Lai. The committee received the contribution in 1935, and the room was dedicated on October 6, 1939, as one of the original 19 Nationality Classrooms.
The first chairman of the committee was Dr. Lai, a graduate student at the University of Pittsburgh. On September 20, 1930, John Tsui was appointed the second chairman of the Chinese Nationality Room Committee. The design for the Chinese Nationality Room was drafted by Teng Kwei, a Beijing artist who had been studying at Harvard, and the architect was Dr. Henry Killam Murphy, the architectural advisor to the Nationalist government. The room was established with the assistance of Ruth Crawford Mitchell, Advisor to the Nationality Rooms, and was dedicated by Dr. Hu Shih, the republic of China's ambassador to the United States.
The room, inspired by the Forbidden City's palace hall, contains one circular table which seats both the students and the professor. Above the table is a relief of a golden, five-clawed Imperial dragon, which is surrounded by a ceiling decorated in the Chinese style. The doorframe is guarded by laughing lions and carved with plum blossoms, the national flower of the Republic of China. On the west wall is a panel decorated with the image of Confucius, to whom the room itself was dedicated. The chalkboard is capable of sliding out, and the base below it displays a carved image of the Bagua.
Today, the Chinese Nationality Room Committee provides a scholarship which allows students to study abroad in the People's Republic of China, Hong Kong, and Taiwan.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Previous Citation
Chinese Nationality Room Committee Collection, 1929-1939, UA.40.04, University of Pittsburgh Archives
Acquisition Information
Transferred to the University Archives by the Nationality Rooms Program on August 3, 2014.
Architectural drawings (Visual works); Clippings (Information artifacts); Correspondence; Financial records; Minutes (Administrative records); Photographs; Chinese Americans -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Universities and colleges -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Classrooms -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; University of Pittsburgh; Murphy, Henry Killam; Lai, Chi Fang; Mitchell, Ruth Crawford; University of Pittsburgh. Nationality Rooms Program. Chinese Nationality Room Committee.; University of Pittsburgh. Nationality Rooms Program; Nationality Rooms (Cathedral of Learning, Pittsburgh, Pa.); Tsui, John H.; Kwei, Teng
- Correspondence with Architect, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence with Architect, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence with Architect, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence with Architect, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence with Architect, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence with Architect, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence with Architect, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence with Architect, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence with Architect, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence with Architect, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence with Architect, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1930-1939 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Financial Statements, 1931-1939 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Committee Meeting Minutes, 1931-1939 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Running Memo, 1929-1939 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Photographs, 1929-1939 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Drawings, Chinese Room Design (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Ceiling Design, Measurements and Estimates (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Publicity, 1929-1939 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- General Correspondence, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- General Correspondence, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- General Correspondence, 1931 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- General Correspondence, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- General Correspondence, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- General Correspondence, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- General Correspondence, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- General Correspondence, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- General Correspondence, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- General Correspondence, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- General Correspondence, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Events, 1942-1959 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Committee Archives Box (Box 6)
  Scope and Content Notes
  This large box contains four smaller, silk covered boxes that originally contained the archives of the Chinese Nationality Room Committee. All five containers are held closed with bone clasps.